{"tossups": [{"question": "This man, who shared leadership with Crixus and Oenomaus, routed Mummius when he attacked against orders. Gaius Claudius Glaber tried to starve this man\u2019s forces while they camped on the slopes of Mount Vesuvius. Many of this man\u2019s supporters were crucified by Crassus along the Appian Way after they lost the Third Servile War. For ten points, name this former gladiator who died in 71 BC while leading a slave revolt against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "An artist from this country was influenced by Marcel Duchamp to weld together 42 bicycle frames. That artist, who filmed the aftermath of a 2008 earthquake in this country, also exhibited one million handmade porcelain sunflower seeds in England\u2019s Tate Modern gallery. For ten points, name this country where artist and political activist Ai Weiwei consulted on the design of a \u201cbird\u2019s nest\u201d stadium built for this country\u2019s 2008 Summer Olympics.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> (or<b> Zhongguo</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s winning side was greatly aided when they learned that an attack at \u201cA-F\u201d would take place; that information came by breaking the JN25 code. Dauntless dive bombers were used to great effect in this battle, as one side sunk the<em> Akagi</em>,<em> Kaga</em> and two other ships while only losing the<em> Yorktown</em>. For ten points, name this battle fought a month after the Battle of Coral Sea, a carrier battle that became the \u201cturning point\u201d of World War II\u2019s Pacific theater.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Midway</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event directly led to the passage of the Sullivan-Hoey Law. The owners of the central location of this event, Max Blanck and Isaac Harris, were acquitted of manslaughter charges when the prosecution was unable to prove that they knew a series of doors were locked. The ILGWU union gained traction in the wake of this event, in which some immigrant workers jumped nine stories to their death. For ten points, name this 1911 fire in a New York City factory.", "answer": "<b> Triangle Shirtwaist</b> factory fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler signed the Treaty of Ryswick to end a lengthy war against a \u201cGrand Alliance\u201d that opposed him. Earlier, this ruler had used the death of Philip IV and a dowry owed to this man\u2019s nation to start the War of the Devolution. This king ended toleration for Huguenots in the Edict of Fontainebleau, which revoked the Edict of Nantes. The death of Cardinal Mazarin began the 72-year-long reign of, for ten points, what absolutist \u201cSun King\u201d of France?", "answer": "<b> Louis XIV</b> [14] Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "He This composer protested in support of Alfred Dreyfus by refusing to perform in Paris in 1899. He included an \u201cArietta\u201d and a tribute to Niels Gade in a ten-book set of 66 short piano pieces, and a tympani roll opens his only<em> Piano Concerto</em>, in A minor. This composer of the<em> Lyric Pieces</em> also wrote incidental music for a Henrik Ibsen play that includes \u201cAnitra\u2019s Dance\u201d and \u201cMorning Mood.\u201d For ten points, name this nationalist Norwegian composer who wrote<em> Peer Gynt</em>.", "answer": "Edvard<b> Grieg</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This project began thanks to a revolution started by the killing of a Chinese civilian and his donkey. Philippe-Jean Bunau-Varilla orchestrated a controversial treaty, later undone by the Torrijos-Carter Treaties, granting the US control over this project. \u201cGunboat diplomacy\u201d against Colombia sparked a Central American country\u2019s independence and the building of, for ten points, what canal that, in 1914, connected the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans?", "answer": "<b> Panama Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this battle in which Andrew Jackson defended a Louisiana port city.", "answer": "Battle of<b> New Orleans</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This mentor of Phog Allen played center on the McGill University football team in the 1890s. Luther Gulick asked this man for advice on keeping members of the Springfield YMCA in shape; this man used a pair of peach baskets in his ensuing invented game. The University of Kansas\u2019 only losing coach in one sport is, ironically, this man. The NBA Hall of Fame is named after, for ten points, what inventor of basketball?", "answer": "James<b> Naismith</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The \u201ctransforming principle\u201d of this molecule was discovered in an experiment on mice by Frederick Griffith. Evidence for this molecule\u2019s purpose was found in a 1952 experiment using sulfur, phosphorous, and bacteriophages. X-ray diffraction pictures taken by Rosalind Franklin helped earn Watson and Crick a Nobel Prize for determining the double helix structure of, for ten points, what molecule that carries genetic instructions?", "answer": "<b> DNA</b> (or<b> deoxyribonucleic acid</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Ibrahim the Mad and Murad the Great were sultans of, for ten points, what empire that, under Mehmed II, conquered Constantinople from the Byzantines in 1453?", "answer": "Alfred<b> Hershey</b> and Martha<b> Chase</b> (accept in either order; accept the<b> Hershey-Chase experiment</b>) (2) The death of a ruler of this empire at the hands of Tamerlane led to an interregnum ended at the Battle of C\u00b8amurlu. An Albanian revolt against this empire was led by a former general named Skanderbeg, and this empire defeated a Christian coalition at the Battle of Varna in 1444. Ibrahim the Mad and Murad the Great were sultans of, for ten points, what empire that, under Mehmed II, conquered Constantinople from the Byzantines in 1453? ANSWER:<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a play by this author, a man who gave away all of his money at a banquet finds a hoard of gold while living in a cave in the wilderness. This author wrote a play in which the images of an armored head, a bloody child, and a crowned child warn a king of Scotland that he cannot be harmed by a man \u201cof woman born,\u201d though the king is later killed by Macduff anyways. For ten points, name this author of the historically inspired tragedies<em> Timon of Athens</em> and<em> Macbeth</em>.", "answer": "William<b> Shakespeare</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "This country tried to kickstart its economy under the \u201cFifty Years of Progress in Five\u201d program of Juscelino Kubitschek. A European-inspired Estado Novo period in this country marked the end of \u201ccoffee with milk\u201d politics. The petroleum company Petrobras was nationalized in, for ten points, what country whose 20th century modernization included Oscar Niemeyer\u2019s designing of a new capital city to replace Rio de Janeiro?", "answer": "Federative Republic of<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The day before this event, the \u201cStennis Compromise\u201d was offered to, and rejected by, its target. This event ended when third-in-command Robert Bork, having been promised a seat on the Supreme Court, followed orders that William Ruckelshaus and Elliot Richardson refused to carry out. October 20, 1973 was the date of, for ten points, what sub-scandal in which Richard Nixon ordered the firing of the special prosecutor in charge of Watergate?", "answer": "<b> Saturday Night Massacre</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A charter in this modern-day state was given to Ferdinando Gorges, who never actually visited the New World, and John Mason. The first ship built by England in the New World</b> <b>was named for Sagadahoc, a colony in this state on the (+)</b> <b>Kennebec River. Mistakes in</b> <b>the 1789 Treaty of Paris led to the Aroostook War in what is now this state. In 1820, after the (*)</b> Missouri Compromise, this state was created by splitting off from Massachusetts. For ten points, name this northeastern state whose capital moved in 1832 from Portland to Augusta.", "answer": "<b> Maine</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Ancient culture on this island included the worship of a woman holding two serpents in her hands, \u201cthe snake goddess,\u201d and its art used the Horns of Consecration motif in honor of a sacred bull. In the second millennium BC, the (+) Thera eruption on Santorini devastated this island to the south; that event and a possible Mycenaean invasion from the mainland may have ended a civilization centered on this island that used the still-undeciphered (*) </b>Linear A script and had its capital at Knossos. For ten points, name this largest Greek island, the home of the Minoan civilization.", "answer": "<b> Crete</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>William Momyer came under fire for suggesting that this group engage only in coastal duties. Members of this group trained at Moton Field. A subgroup of these people gained</b> <b>a famous nickname after painting the (+)</b> <b>tails of their P-47s red. A member of this</b> <b>group, Chief Anderson, took Eleanor Roosevelt on a test flight that helped speed up the (*) </b> desegregation of the military. An Alabama university names, for ten points, what group of African American World War II pilots?", "answer": "<b> Tuskegee Airmen</b> (accept<b> 477th Bombardment</b> Group or<b> 332nd Fighter</b> Group)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this man\u2019s attempts at unification, he allied with the Soviet Union after signing a manifesto with Adolph Joffe. To gain the support of the Beiyang Army, this man promised</b> <b>the presidency to Yuan (+)</b> <b>Shikai while orchestrating the Xinhai [shin-hai] Revolution</b> <b>against emperor Pu Yi. This man believed in nationalism, democracy, and livelihood - the (*)</b> \u201cthree principles of the people\u201d - and founded the Kuomintang. For ten points, name this first president of the Republic of China.", "answer": "<b> Sun</b> Yat-sen", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In this war, the first African American to command an American military unit, Oliver Law, was killed at the Battle of Brunete. The Conference of Nyon condemned Italian</b> <b>submarine attacks in this war, which included Operation (+)</b> <b>R\u00a8ugen. The term \u201cfifth</b> <b>column\u201d was coined by Emilio Mola during this war. In this war, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade fought alongside republicans and the (*)</b> German Condor Legion bombed Guernica. For ten points, name this 1936 to 1939 war that ended when Francisco Franco captured Madrid.", "answer": "<b> Spanish Civil</b> War  (1) <b>A British attempt to invade this country was thwarted by Alexandre Petion\u2019s</b> <b>artillery. Yellow fever hurt Charles Leclerc\u2019s attempts to put down a rebellion in this</b> <b>country. After this country gained its independence, Jean-Jacques (+)</b> <b>Dessalines</b> <b>[dess-ah-leen] became governor-general. Napoleon was prompted to sell Louisiana to</b> <b>the United States after losing this modern day country to a (*)</b> slave revolt. Toussaint L\u2019Ouverture\u2019s slave rebellion took place in, for ten points, what country that shares Hispaniola with the Dominican Republic? ANSWER: Republic of<b> Haiti</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}